Inventory of the Papers of Neill H. Alford, Jr. 1942-1989
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Neill H. Alford, Jr. 1942-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 90-3
This collection consists of 13 boxes (5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Neill H. Alford, Jr., born in 1919, received his B.A. from The Citadel in 1940. After serving in Europe during World War II, he obtained his LL.B. in 1947 from the University of Virginia. In 1966 he received a J.S.D. from Yale University.
Alford began his long teaching career at the University as soon as he earned his degree in 1947 and became a full professor in 1956. After that time, he was absent from the Law School for only brief periods: during the 1961-62 academic year, when he held the Chair of International Law at the Naval War College, and from 1974 to 1976, when he was dean and Joseph Henry Lumpkin Professor of Law at the University of Georgia. Upon his return to the Law School, Alford became Percy Brown, Jr. Professor of Law. He held this post until his retirement in 1990.
Professor Alford's professional interests include administrative law, international law, economic warfare, legal history, and trusts and estates. The author of many legal works, Alford is perhaps best known for his Cases and Materials on Decedents' Estates and Trusts.
Scope and Content Information
This collection is comprised of personal correspondence, records and briefs from Alford's private legal practice, speeches and articles, and teaching materials. Material dealing with Alford's legal practice primarily concerns wills and estates. Alford wrote and spoke on a variety of topics, and his articles and speeches fill 45 folders. By far the greatest portion of the collection is devoted to teaching materials, principally for courses in international law, legal history, and trusts and estates.
Contents List
- Adminstration of Estates n.d. (Box 1)
- Agenda, Plans for Memo, etc. 1942, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
- Rena Lou Alford 1985 (Box 1)
- American College of Probate Counsel 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- American Legal Institutions 1951-1952 (Box 1)
- American Society for Legal History 1975-1976 (Box 1)
- Archer Anderson, Jr. Memo n.d. (Box 1)
- Appointment as Legal Advisor 1972 (Box 1)
- Army: Delay Obligors 1968 (Box 1)
- Army Records 1965-1967 (Box 1)
- Army Reserve 1968 (Box 1)
- Augmented Estate 1983, 1985 (Box 1)
- John Thomas Baker and Charles Maechling 1975 (Box 1)
- Bar 1972 (Box 1)
- Bar Examiners 1967 (Box 1)
- Bar of Georgia: Admission 1973-1975 (Box 1)
- Colonel Paul Benson, Jr. 1986 (Box 1)
- Biographical Information n.d., 1974, 1983, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Bookbinding 1977-78, 1980-81 (Box 1)
- Bookboxer 1986 (Box 1)
- Judge John Boyd 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Brabson Paper 1971 (Box 1)
- Bridgewater College 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
- California State Bar: Exam Questions 1974 (Box 1)
- Case Book: 6th Edition 1978, 1980-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Charlottesville-Albemarle Bar Association 1975 (Box 1)
- Charlottesville Parking Ordinance n.d. (Box 1)
- Cherokee Law n.d. (Box 2)
- Commissions on Specific Legacies n.d. (Box 2)
- Committee for Child Protection 1972 (Box 2)
- Committee on Contractual Relations 1969-1970 (Box 2)
- Committee on Wills, Trusts and Estates 1983, 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Committee on Virginia Status 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Communications 1946-48, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Continuing Legal Education 1972 (Box 2)
- Correspondence: Miscellaneous 1963-64, 1972-74, 1976-79, 1981, 7 folders (Box 2)
- Walker Cowen Fund 1988 (Box 2)
- Lawrence Cranberg Case 1969-70, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Charles Cullen: Legal History Project 1971 (Box 2)
- Dea Dagen & Yves Coty 1972 (Box 2)
- Hardy Cross Dillard 1971 (Box 2)
- David Dorset 1986 (Box 2)
- William G. Eckhardt 1959-65 (Box 3)
- Professor Eskridge 1985 (Box 3)
- John T. Fey n.d. (Box 3)
- First Amendment: "Virginia Advocate" Funding 1989 (Box 3)
- Daniel J. Fleming, III 1969 (Box 3)
- James Fletcher: Correspondence 1958, 1966, 1979, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Ford Transactions 1965 (Box 3)
- Charles W. Fore: Correspondence 1972 (Box 3)
- Foundation Press 1977 (Box 3)
- Jack Fox: Will 1969 (Box 3)
- William P. Francisco 1971-72, 1977-79, 1985 (Box 3)
- Future Interests 1983 (Box 3)
- Funding of Gay Student Union 1984 (Box 3)
- George Mason College 1972 (Box 3)
- Goals Committee n.d. (Box 3)
- W. Clyde Gouldman 1969 (Box 3)
- Graduate Committee n.d. (Box 3)
- Ronald E. Gregory 1989 (Box 3)
- Gene Gressley: Correspondence 1983 (Box 3)
- Ronald Griffin 1986 (Box 3)
- Christine Halphen 1986 (Box 3)
- Daniel Hartnett 1969 (Box 3)
- William H. Hinkle 1972 (Box 3)
- Waller Horsley 1986 (Box 3)
- House Bill 801 1987 (Box 3)
- Lawrence W. I'anson: Testimonial Dinner 1981 (Box 3)
- Penelope Ideson: Correspondence 1966-68, 1971-74 (Box 3)
- Inheritance Tax Policy 1980, 1982 (Box 3)
- Intrafamily Transfers for Consideration 1981 (Box 3)
- JAG (Judge Advocacy General) School 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Herbert Alan Johnson 1973-75 (Box 3)
- Joint Committee on Continuing Legal Education 1970-71, 1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Joint Subcommittee of Courts of Justice Committee 1973 (Box 4)
- Ronald Griffith Jones n.d. (Box 4)
- Peter J. Knop 1971 (Box 4)
- Robert Landel: Correspondence 1974 (Box 4)
- Henry Laurens Papers 1966 (Box 4)
- Legal Classics Library 1977, 1982 (Box 2 folders)
- Report to Legislature n.d. (Box 4)
- Geoffrey Lester 1972 (Box 4)
- Letters of Recommendation 1972-74, 1977-78 (Box 2 folders)
- Steve Levine 1986, 1988 (Box 4)
- Libraries Committee 1986 (Box 4)
- Library Storage Committee 1984-1986 (Box 4)
- Rutgers School of Law: Sarah Love 1978 (Box 4)
- Lucayan Beach Pirate Treasure 1960s (Box 4)
- Madison Hall: Society of Fellows n.d. (Box 4)
- Daniel M. Maher, Jr. 1971 (Box 4)
- Ralph Main 1972 (Box 4)
- Prof. Joseph McKnight 1985 (Box 4)
- John C. McCoid 1972 (Box 4)
- Myres McDougal 1965-66 (Box 4)
- Regina C. McGranery 1971-72 (Box 4)
- Paul G. McIntire 1969 (Box 4)
- D. J. Meador 1978-79 (Box 4)
- Dean Richard Merrill 1985-86 (Box 4)
- Roger Miller 1968 (Box 4)
- S. Lee Miller: Motor Vehicle Insurance n.d. (Box 4)
- Minnesota Bar Examiners 1977-78 (Box 4)
- Minnesota Board of Law Examiners 1972-76, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Notes n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
- Susan Moore: "The Marriage License as a Raping License" 1984 (Box 5)
- David R. Mummery 1967 (Box 5)
- Robert L. Musick, Jr. 1971 (Box 5)
- Nash Memorial 1982-83 (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings 1966, 1968 (Box 5)
- North: Codicils 1983 (Box 5)
- Gary K. Oldehoff 1985-86 (Box 5)
- Mrs. Oliver 1972 (Box 5)
- Mrs. Patterson: Tax Returns 1970 (Box 5)
- Richard F. Pence: Shumate memo 1978 (Box 5)
- Personal Appointment Letters 1956, 1962, 1973-76, 1979 (Box 5)
- Personal Files 1961-62, 1974-77, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Justice Richard H. Poff 1978, 1988 (Box 5)
- Practice: Ancell v. Ancell 1957, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Practice: State of Arizona v. W. A. Coerver 1966 (Box 5)
- Practice: B. Drummond Ayres Case 1966 (Box 5)
- Practice: Battle v. Jessup 1960, 1963, 1973, 1976-77, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Practice: Beverly v. Turner 1976 (Box 6)
- Practice: Brooks v. Boyd n.d. (Box 6)
- Practice: John Woodfin Burress Trust 1972 (Box 6)
- Practice: B. F. Dillard Estate 1959-60 (Box 6)
- Practice: Hagemann-Woodward Estate 1972, 1975 (Box 6)
- Practice: MacConochie Will 1956-57 (Box 6)
- Practice: National Bank and Trust Company v. Nuttycombe 1969-70, 11 folders (Box 6-7)
- Smith v. Moore 1962(?), 5 folders (Box 7)
- Practice: Smyth v. Anderson 1977 (Box 7)
- Practice: White v. National Bank and Trust Company 1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Proposed Probate Tax Regulations 1983 (Box 7)
- "George Wythe Randolph and the Confederate Elite" 1983 (Box 7)
- Research Leave 1986 (Box 7)
- Retirement Plans 1977 (Box 7)